好的，下午好，无论你在哪里。
Okay, good afternoon, wherever you are.
嗯，大家都能听到我说话吗，
Um, can everybody hear me,
快速测试一下语音。
quick sound check, make sure.
是的，是好的。
Yeah you're fine.
好的，谢谢。
Good, thank you.
那么今天我们就来谈一谈，
So today we're going to talk about,
我没有具体的日程安排，
I don't really have a specific agenda
但基本上我们的计划是回答问题，
but basically the plan is to try to answer questions
你可能对上一个实验或之前的实验有什么问题。
that you might have about these last lab or the previous labs.
所以我要采取的方法是，
Um, so the approach I'm going to take,
今天，我要介绍一下我们的解决方案。
today, is, I'm gonna walk through the staff solutions.
尤其是我自己的解决方案，
In particularly my own solutions,
我会讨论一下它们，
I'm going to discuss them
希望在我们讨论解决方案时，
and hopefully as we go through the staff solutions,
你可以打断，
um, you can jump in
如果我没有回答某个问题，
if I don't answer a particular question,
或者稍等一下，
um or, wait a little bit,
因为我把你们问的所有问题，
because I put all the questions that you've asked
至少在今天上午 11 点之前的，
at least before eleven am this morning,
在最后的课堂讲稿中，
in the lecture notes at the bottom
我们会试着去全部过一遍。
and we'll try to go through that.
我将从页表（pagetable）实验开始，
I'm gonna start with the pagetable lab,
因为大多数问题都是关于页表的实验，
because most questions were about the pagetable lab,
部分原因是因为它是最难的实验。
and partly because it was the hardest labs.
所以也许首先有几点解释，
Um, and so maybe a couple of comments
在深入到技术部分之前，
before diving into the technical part of this,
我们来大体上谈一下页表实验。
let's talk a little bit about the pagetable lab in general.
正如你可能观察到的，
And you know as you probably observed,
它实际上只有几行代码，
you know it's actually a few lines of code,
在解决方案上，
in terms of the solution,
但是，不幸的是，必须调试问题。
but, it unfortunately has, you know, had to debug problems.
而且，有一个原因是，
And, you know, there's one reason is that
当 bug 真的出现时，
when actually bug shows up,
结果是相当极端的，
you know the outcomes are pretty extreme
就像在最坏的情况下，
like in the worst case,
可能你们中的一些人观察到了最坏的情况，
probably some of you observed that the worst case,
QEMU 停止或 xv6 停止，
QEMU stops or xv6 stops,
不再打印输出，就是这样，
there's no output being printed anymore, and that's it,
你的工作就是找出到底哪里出了问题，
you know it's your job to figure out actually what went wrong,
在最好的情况下，你会遇到某种内核错误（kernel panic），
in the best case you get sort of kernel panic,
取决于，也许这只是一个起点，
depending you know maybe just a starting point
或者追查问题的真正根源是错误本身，
or for tracking down what the actual source of the problem is panic itself,
可能与其他什么有关，
it's probably related to something else,
内核的一些常量被破坏，
something the invariant that the kernel got broken,
但你知道早些时候在外面的某个地方，
but you know somewhere out earlier,
可能在设置页表时，
probably when you set up the pagetables,
你做错了什么最后引起错误，
you did something wrong at the end causes panic to go off,
你得追踪到底是怎么回事。
you have to track down what's going on.
所以代码行数更少，很难调试问题，
So fewer lines of code, hard to debug problems,
在生产环境，恶劣的环境中去调试。
in produce a harsh environment, to debug.
如果你做内核调试或内核编程，
If you do in the kernel debugging or kernel programming,
你知道，编程环境，调试环境，
you know programming environment, debugging environment,
更是，你知道的，恶劣的，
is more, you know unforgiven,
正如 Robert 在第一节课中提到的，
as Robert mentioned in the first lecture,
是做内核编程的难点之一。
is one of the hard parts about basically doing kernel programming.
为了让你感觉好点，
And that's you know just to make you feel better,
这不仅对你来说很难，
this is not just hard for you,
你知道对我们来说也很难。
you know actually hard for your staff.
无论是在帮助你方面，
Both in terms of helping you
实际上我们做这些实验，
and actually you know we do these labs
我们也会遇到类似的问题，
and we make similar problems,
我们可能有更多的经验追踪 bug ，
you know we probably have more experience at tracking bugs down,
但是你知道它们确实需要时间。
but you know they just, they do take time.
所以我们在帮你的时候，
Um, so we're helping you,
往往也很难，
you know the, tends to be hard too,
因为有一些很小的代码片段，
because there's some small fragment of code,
有一个细节可能有问题，
there's one detail something probably wrong
他们要弄清楚到底什么是小细节，
and they're figuring out actually what little detail is,
这并不容易。
it's not easy.
当然有一些问题，
Of course some of the problems,
我们以前见过，我们也认识到，
we've seen before and we're recognizing,
例如，我们自己没有犯同样的错误，
for example we didn't make the same mistake ourselves,
但是你们发现的其他一些，
but other ones you discovered
各种不同的破坏内核的方式，
all kinds of different ways of breaking the kernel,
我们以前没见过的。
that we hadn't seen before.
所以这很难，
So this is just hard,
根据我们的经验，
I think this is, in our experience,
对于虚拟内存，这在以往也总是很难，
this is historically always hard with virtual memory,
所以每次第一个虚拟内存实验出现的时候，
so every time the first virtual memory lab comes around,
不论在 6.S081 中或它的前身 6.828 中，
either in 6.S081 or its predecessor in 6.828,
事实就是这样
it has been the case
你知道那往往是最难的实验，
that you know that tends to be the hardest lab,
在所有实验室中，
of all the labs
你知道的，原因有很多，
and you know for a number of reasons,
一种是恶劣环境，
one you know the harsh environment,
这些 bug 很特殊，
you know the the bugs are spectacular
还有部分原因是你还没有
and partly because you haven't done
很丰富的内核编程经验，
that much kernel programming experience yet,
所以这可以说是第一个实验，
and so this is sort of the first lab
所有这些都结合在一起了。
with all those things come together.
今年，我们试着让实验变得更简单，
This year, we tried to make lab simpler,
事实上，这是一个新的实验，
in fact, this is a new lab,
一个我们之前没有的实验。
a lab we did not have that lab.
希望实际上，
In the hopes that actually
使引入或转换到虚拟内存变得更容易，
make this introduction or the transition into a virtual memory easier,
在某些方面我认为是成功的，
in some ways I think it was successful,
在其他方面，这仍然很难，
in other ways, you know it's still hard,
所以我们不太清楚，
so we don't really know,
什么是最简单的方法，
maybe about the easiest way
引入虚拟内存编程。
of actually introducing virtual memory programming is.
下周的惰性分配实验，
Lab, the lab next week, the lazy lab
实际上曾经是第一个虚拟内存实验。
is actually a lab that used to be the first virtual memory lab.
我猜你们今年会发现，
And my suspicion is that you'll find this year,
实验比去年的要容易，
lab easier than the students found it last year,
因为你现在在虚拟内存方面有了更多的背景知识。
because you now have much more background in virtual memory.
好的，所以这是一个很好的停止点，
Okay, so that's, there is a good point to stop,
这里我想提出的几个高层次的观点，
this was a couple high level points I wanted to make,
在跳到更具技术性和更多细节之前，
before jumping into more technical with more details,
所以，如果你有任何问题，现在就是提问题的好时机。
so if you have any questions, is a great time to ask questions.
好的。
Okay.
让我们，快点，你知道，你们中的一些人问到这个，
Let's, quickly, you know some of you asked for this,
非常快速地回顾一下具体设置是什么，
very quick review exactly what you were what the setting is,
所以，基本上，设置页表，
and so, basically, the settings pagetables,
我们在右边画出物理内存，
and we have physical memory draw here, right side,
你知道物理内存，包含部分设备，
you know the physical memory, consist of partly about devices,
它们在这个 0x00 以及更多的零之上，
and they live above this 0x zero zero and many more zeros,
然后这里是 DRAM 芯片。
and then here basically dram chips.
我们知道，
And we know that
QEMU 将内核文本数据放在这里，
QEMU actually puts the kernel, the kernel text data, right here,
在 0x00 之上，
at the above 0x zero zero zero,
这就是内核所在的地方，
so that's where the kernel lives,
其中一种可能是，
and one way it may be,
擦掉这个来使用内核。
earse this a little bit to use the kernel.
你知道从字面上它是什么意思，
And you know basically literally what it means,
你知道这是什么，内核就是用户指令，
you know what this is what the kernel is user instructions,
是你已经看到的汇编指令的二进制版本，
binary versions of the assembling instructions that you've seen,
还有一些数据结构位于这些地址。
and there's also some data structures located at these addresses.
好的，这就是内存的部分，
Okay, so that's the memory part of it
然后在另一边，我们有 CPU ，
and then on the other side we got our CPU,
它执行指令。
that executes instructions.
CPU 有很多内部指令，
CPU has a bunch of internal state,
并且有一些寄存器，
and has some registers,
你知道 x0 或 r0 等，
you know whatever x0 or r0 blah blah blah,
还有程序计数器。
and you know maybe the program counter.
你知道在 xv6 启动的时候，
And you know when xv6 starts,
程序计数器包含值 Ox8000 。
you know the program counter contains this value Ox8000.
这就是它的方式，
And that's the way you know,
CPU 查看这个地址，
the CPU knows that basically look at that address
找出第一条指令，
to find you know the first instruction,
它查看第一个指令并解码指令，
it looks at the first instruction decode instruction
然后更新需要更新的 CPU 状态。
and updates whatever CPU state that needs to be updated.
页表和其他一些组件，
You know pagetables and sort of component to it
这个地址包含，
that you know the addresses you know
CPU 命令或指令，
the CPU orders or the instructions are part of the instructions,
比如，跳到某个特定的地址，
like you know jump to some particular address
并且这些地址通常是虚拟地址。
and those addresses are typically or most commonly or will be virtual addresses.
这是虚拟地址，由 MMU 管理。
And now there's virtual addresses, go to that [] is called the MMU.
然后转换成物理地址，
And then you translate into physical addresss,
并且索引到
um, and that is allowing [] index into
内存的 IO 部分，
either the IO part of the memory
或者内存的 DRAM 部分。
or the DRAM part the memory.
为了控制这个转换发生，
To control how this translation happens,
你知道这里有 satp 寄存器，
you know there's this satp register,
它包含页表的根地址，
which contains the root of the pagetable
即当前运行的页表。
of the current running page table.
如果是零，
And if there's zero,
那么就不会进行转换，
then there's basically no translation going on
并且虚拟地址直接指向物理地址，
and the virtual address is literally directly physical address,
因此，当处理器启动时，
so when the processor actually starts up,
satp 中没有值，
there's no value in satp
当程序计数器是 0x... 时，
and when the program counter as an 0x...,
物理地址也是[]，
you know basically the physical address is also []
CPU 从该特定位置获取指令。
and basically [] the CPU fetches the instruction from that particular location.
一旦，
As soon as you know the,
一旦 satp 包含非零值，
as soon as the satp actually contains a non zero value,
那么，例如，可能，在这里的某个地方，
then, you know, for example maybe so somewhere in here
把图片延伸一些，
to draw them make something extended pictures a bit further,
我们知道内核实际上最多有 128 兆字节。
we know that the kernel actually has a maximum 128 megabytes.
所以基本上这些都是空闲内存，
And so basically this is all free memory,
从这里到这里是空闲内存，
from here to there is free memory
空闲内存放在 kalloc.c 中的列表中，
and free memory is put on the list in kalloc.c
像你之前看到的那样。
as you've seen before.
并且，这里的某个地方也是根页表，
And, so somewhere in here is also the root pagetable
你知道的，内核页表，
for you know a kernel pagetable,
可能这里有一些页面，
so maybe here's some page,
是根页表目录。
and that it's the root pagetable directory.
一旦我们加载该值，
As soon as we load that value
该值对应的物理地址，
the address of the physical address of that value
进入 satp 地址和寄存器，
into the satp address and register,
假设这个地址是 0x7ff... ，
let's say this maybe this addresses 0x7 you know f f blah blah,
一个低于 120 兆字节的地址，
something just below one hundred twenty megabytes,
所以在内存空闲空间中，
so in that free space of memory
在 satp 中地址，
below that address in satp,
然后，在这时，处理器或 MMU
then, at that point you know the processor or MMU
将使用根页表执行
will use the root pagetables to actually
从虚拟地址到物理地址的转换。
do the translation from virtual to physical address.
你可以把这整个东西，
And you can think of this, this particular whole thing,
像是一个盒子，
sort of being a single sort of box,
你知道，将它们整合在一起。
you know integrated you know, together.
你对这张高层次图片有问题吗，
And you have questions about this high-level picture,
在继续之前，
before keep them going,
所以这里要记住的一个关键点是，
so one of the key points to remember here is
页面状态本身也驻留在内存中。
that the page statements themselves also live in memory.
好吧。
Okay.
好的，那我们跳到，
Okay, so let's jump down to,
页表实验的第一部分，
the first part of the pagetable lab,
也就是第一部分，
namely part one where you have to
为 init 程序打印页表，
print the pagetable for the init program,
你知道的，解释基本上都在图 3.4 ，
and um, and you know explain it basically in terms of this figure three four
图 3.4 就在这里。
and figure three four is right here.
图 3.4 ，
Figure three four,
这是图 3.4 ，显示用户地址空间，
and this is figure three four shows the user address space,
让我们看看的用户地址空间，
just let's look at the user address space for a second,
在进入细节之前，
before we are going to detail,
我们在底部有文本，
so we have the text at the bottom,
这就是程序的指令，
so this is the instructions of the program,
从地址 0 开始，
starting address zero
上方是数据、全局变量，驻留在那里，
above the instructions are data, global variables, live there,
然后我们会讨论守护页，
then there's something called the guard page we'll talk about,
然后是用户程序的堆栈，
and then it's the stack of the user program,
内核有自己的堆栈，
so the kernel has its own stack,
多个堆栈，
multiple stack
用户程序有自己的堆栈，
user program has its own stack
缓冲区，也就是所谓堆内存，空闲内存，
and buff again is basically what's called heap memory, free memory,
我们可以使用 sbrk 获得更多内存，
you know we can get more memory using sbrk,
sbrk 基本上指向用户地址空间的顶部，
so sbrk basically points to the top of the user address space,
我们想要增加它，
we want to grow it,
我们调用 sbrk 系统调用
we called sbrk system call to grow
来增加底部部分，
grow the top of the, to grow the bottom part,
你知道增加到堆里去，
you know up into the heap,
我们还从上一节课中知道，顶端，
we also know that the top, there from the last lecture,
有两个页面，
that there are two pages,
两个特别的页面， trampoline 和 trapframe 页面。
two special pages the trampoline and the trapframe page.
trampoline 页包含了命令，
And the trampoline page, you know contains the instructions to the basically,
进出内核的转换的命令，
transition in and out of the kernel,
trapframe 是一个很方便的地方，
the trapframe is a convenient place,
存储一些状态，当我们跳入内核时，
you know to stores from state and when we jump into the kernel,
因为我们就需要内核，一旦使用寄存器，
because we need the kernel once use registers,
我们可以使用寄存器，
we can use the registers,
因为用户空间程序还有一些在使用。
because the user space program still has some in use.
我不会太多谈论 tramframe 和 trampoline ，
I'm not gonna talk much about tramframe and trampoline at all,
你知道的，它们在这里。
you know they are there.
好的，在这张图片的下面一点，
OK, so here this picture a little below,
你知道就在那里，是打印出来的，
you know is actually there, printout from,
当我运行它时，从 init 打印出来的。
when I run it, from init.
这是 exec 的第一次成功调用，
This the first successful call of exec right,
我们知道 init 代码中有一些 exec 系统调用，
so we know that init code makes some system call exec,
对于程序 init ，正好在 exec 的末尾，
for the program init and just at the end of the exec,
我们打印出那个页表。
we're printing out that pagetable.
有几个我们可以观察到的东西，
And so a couple things that we, many things we can observe,
关于这个特殊的页表，
about this particular pagetable,
首先，
so first of all you know,
除了打印出物理 pte ，
we in addition to printing out the physical ptes
物理地址也打印出了标志。
and the physical address is also printing out the flags.
你可以看到，这里的标志是 1 ，
And you can see here that here flag is one,
基本上就是这个转换，
and basically says this translation,
或者这个中间页像这个一样，
or this, intermediate page is that similar here,
是有效的独立页，
you know is valid independent page,
这对应于二级页面，
and this basically corresponds to the level two page
然后第二个对应于……。
and then the second one corresponds to the level....
我很抱歉我刚才画错了箭头，
I'm sorry I just threw the arrows wrong,
所以我暂停一下。
so that's why a pause for a second.
在顶端，这是顶层页表，
At the top, this is the top level pagetable,
这个，指向这个特定的页表，
this, you know points to this particular pagetable,
这个，指向那个特定的页表。
and this points to that particular pagetable.
或者这就是地址，我们使用一种速记，用来表示，
Or that's the address, we're pointing to a sort of shorthand for saying,
这是特定页面的基础地址。
that is the base address for that particular page.
你知道，这些页面有 4096 字节，
And you know these pages 4096 bytes,
大小是页的大小，
it's size of page size,
除以 64 会得到 512 个条目。
and so divided by 64 its going to get 512 entries.
好的，我们看这个地址空间的底部部分。
Okay so we'll see is the bottom part of this address space.
对于 init ，实际上只有有三个页面，
You know, for init basically has actually all this, has three pages, only three pages,
我们做几件事，
and we do a couple things
可以把这三页区分出来。
that we can discern from the three pages.
我们知道，底部页面对应虚拟地址零，
We know that the bottom page which basically corresponds to the virtual address zero,
这个物理地址， 87f640 。
this physical address, you know eight seven six four zero.
你可以从我们之前的图片中知道，
And you know from our previous picture,
那就在空闲内存中的某个地方，
that is somewhere in that free memory,
内核可以从中分配页面。
that the kernel has available to allocate pages from.
最后你看到的是标志，
And the final things you see the flags,
我们看到标志 1f ，
we see the flags one f,
所以它意味着读取位设置，
so it means that read bit set,
有效位设置，读取位设置，写位设置，执行位设置，用户位设置，
valid bit set, read bit set, w bit set, execute bit set and u bit set,
所以这个页面可以同时包含数据和文本，
so this page can contain both data and text,
这些权限允许用户程序
and these permissions allow the user program
在对应的内存执行指令，
to execute instructions from or to the right memory,
并从用户空间执行。
and do it from user space.
好的，那么也许最有趣的问题是，
Okay, so then maybe the most interesting question is
第一页有什么问题。
like what's up with page one.
作为一个提示，
And you know as a hint,
你知道，第一页只有 f ，
you know see that page one only has f
而没有设置 u 标志位。
and not the u bit set.
所以，你知道第一页是什么吗。
So, you know what is the page one.
有人知道吗。
Anybody.
是不是守护页。
Is it the guard page.
是的，是守护页。
Yeah, it's the guard page right.
守护页映射到，
So the guard page is mapped,
因为它包含 v 标志，
because it has a v in it,
而没有设置 u 标志，
but it has not u bit set,
所以任何用户指令试图，
so any user instruction that tries to,
因此，如果用户程序运行超过它的堆栈，
so if a user program runs off its stack,
堆栈从顶部向下增长，
so the stack grows from the top down,
所以即使它真的有更多，
so even if it actually has more,
堆栈足够大，可以容纳 4096 ，
stack is big enough for 4096 are completely full,
然后用户程序，你知道的，把东西放到到堆栈上，
and then user program, you know puts something on the stack,
堆栈在[]上，它将增长到守护页。
stack on the [], it will grow into the guard page.
并且因为没有设置 u 标志位，
And because the u bit is not set,
我们会在内核中得到页面错误或陷阱，
we gotta get a page fault or a trap into the kernel,
因为 MMU 不能转换地址到，
because the MMU cannot translate to address to,
不能将守护页上的地址转换为物理地址，
cannot address cannot translate any addresses on the guard page to physical address,
因为没有设置 u 标志位，
because the [] not having a u bit
这会禁止转换。
basically forbids the translation.
好的，第二页是什么。
Okay, what is that page two.
有人知道吗？
Any, Anybody.
堆栈？
Stack?
是的，这是堆栈页，
Yup, that's the stack page
堆栈页有 4096 字节，
and so again the stack page for forty four thousand ninety six bytes
你会看到，对于权限，这是精心设计的。
and you'll see that's completely elaborate in terms of permissions.
它包含所有权限，
And it has you know everything,
我们能不能把它的权限调得更严格一些。
could we set it up tighter if we wanted to.
是的，我想可以禁用执行位。
Yeah I think you could disable the executive bit.
是的，你可以，对 x 位来说，
Yeah, you probably could execute the x bit,}
这将禁止运行堆栈上任何程序代码。
that would forbid run any program code on the stack.
所以，如果你在运行时生成代码并将其放入堆栈，
So if you generate code on the fly and put it on the stack,
你就不能去执行，
you wouldn't to be able to execute,
你知道这可能是件好事。
you know that maybe probably a good thing.
所以我们可以把权限设置更严格一些。
And so we could have been a little bit tighter.
好的。
Okay, um.
所以这是这个的最下面的部分，
So that's basically the bottom part of this,
页表，
the pagetable,
现在让我们来看看剩下的条目，
so now let's look at the remaining entries,
只剩下两个条目了。
so basically only two remaining entries.
也许标志位是最能说明问题的部分。
And maybe the flag bits are the most telling part of this.
这里的 7 ，表示可读，可写，可用。
So seven, you know means you know read write and valid work.
那么这个是什么，
And so what do we think, that one is
也许我先分析另一个页的权限，
and maybe I'll do the other one too,
b 是 1001 （误：应该是 1011），
so b is I think one zero zero one,
设置了 x 和可用位，
so presumably x and valid,
那么 511 是什么呢？
so what do we think five eleven is.
有人知道吗。
Anybody.
trampoline 和 trap 页面？
The trampoline and trap page?
对，那么， 511 可能是 trampoline ，
Yeah so the, and probably five eleven is definitely trampoline correct,
因为它设置了 x 位，
because it has the x bit set,
所以我们可以执行，
so we must be executed
或者我们允许从该页面执行指令。
or we're allowing instructions to be executed from that page.
所以这一定是 trampoline ，
So that must be a trampoline
我们允许对那个页面进行读写，
and we're allowing read write you know to the to that page,
所以这可能就是 trapframe 页面，
so that's probably the trapframe page,
因为这是我们用来恢复和保存寄存器的那个页。
because that's the one we used to restore and save registers in.
好的，需要注意的一件重要的事是，
Okay, one of the things, a important thing to note is
这里没有设置 u 标志位，
there's no u bit right then,
那么这意味着什么呢，
so what does that mean,
这意味着用户程序不能执行指令，
that means that the user program can actually not execute the instructions,
页 510 作为 trampoline 页面，
that are actually at five ten as a trampoline page,
也不能对该页的写入。
and can't be the write to that page.
因此，只有内核可以从那里执行指令，
So only the kernel can execute instructions from there
而且它只能读写。
and it can only read and write.
所以内核要做这件事，
So basically like the kernel's gonna be doing this before the,
当用户页表还在使用时，
while still using the user pagetable,
是不是这个意思。
right, that's kind of the point.
使得，正如你所知道的， Robert 在上节课中讲解的，
Exactly as you know, Robert explained last lecture,
这就是从用户到内核的过渡，
this is like just for the transition from user to kernel,
在我们跳到之前，
and before we jump to,
在我们将内核页表加载到 satp 寄存器之前，
before we load the kernel pagetable in satp register,
我们需要，
we need a little bit of,
内核需要一些内存来完成它的工作。
you know the kernel needs a little bit of memory to actually do his job.
好的。
Okay.
所以在一些事情上，
So in a couple of things,
这张图片有意思的地方。
then maybe interesting of this picture.
是的，所有的地址都是 87f630 ，
Yeah, so we all in all these addresses go eight seven six three zero,
87f620 ， 87f640 ， 87f610 ，
eight six two, four, seven one of,
这些页面或内存
these are all pages or memory
在内核内存范围内，
in that range of kernel memory
它们是空闲的。
that is you know it's basically free, right.
那么这些地址在物理内存中是连续的吗？
And are these addresses are contiguous in physical memory.
有人知道吗。
Anybody.
不是，它们不一定连续。
No they don't have to be.
不，它们不一定连续，是的，
No, they don't have to be in the are, correct,
你知道吗，看这个， 87f6400 ，
you know look at this, you know seven six four zero zero,
如果是连续的，
if it contiguous,
下一个地址应该是 87f6500 ，
the next address would have been eight seven six you know six five zero,
但事实并非如此。
and it isn't it.
所以关于页表的一个很酷的事情是，
So there's you know one of the cool things about pagetables is
尽管你使用的虚拟地址空间是连续的，
that even though maybe you do virtual address space is contiguous,
物理地址空间，
the physical address space
或与连续虚拟地址对应的物理页面，
or the physical pages that go along with a continuous virtual addresses
不一定是连续的。
are not don't have to be continuous.
因此，这给了内核很大的灵活性，
So this gives the kernel a lot of flexibility
在分配和释放页面方面。
in terms of allocation and freeing pages.
好的。
Okay.
关于第一部分，有什么问题吗。
Any questions about this part one.
我有一个问题。
I had a question.
嗯。
Yeah.
你能稍微解释一下 sbrk 吗，
Could you explain the sbrk a little,
如果我们要在未来的讲座中介绍，
also if we are going to cover in a future lecture,
那么也许我们可以先讲一点。
then maybe we can like just a small.
对，其实我们，
Yeah actually we, let me,
我将在星期三谈论它。
I'm going to talk about it on Wednesday.
这实际上是惰性分配实验的话题。
And it actually will be the topic of the lazy lab.
那么我可能在星期三回答这个问题，
So let me maybe responed the question to Wednesday,
如果到时候还不太清楚，请再问一遍。
and then that's not clear enough, please ask it again.
好的，谢谢。
Sounds good, thank you.
有一个问题。
So had a question.
所以，我记得书上说，
So, I remember that the book said
trampoline 和 trapframe 位于地址空间的顶部。
trampoline and the trapframe were at the top of the address space.
而在这里，它位于第一个根页面，
Right here, it stops at like the first the root pagetable
索引是 255 而不是 511 。
indexes at two five five not five one one.
好问题，很好，很高兴你问我。
Yeah brilliant question, very good, I'm glad you asked.
我在 Q&A 问题中看到了，我打算讨论一下，
I saw in the Q&A questions and I was planning to talk about it,
但是，我忘了。
but of course I've forgot.
所以，是的，这里发生了什么，
So yeah what's going on here,
为什么是 255 而不是 511 。
why is two five five not five eleven.
我们总说 trampoline 位于地址空间的顶端，
Yeah, we always say the trampoline lives at the top of the address space,
它所在的地址空间的顶部，
while the top of the address space where it is,
你知道的，指向顶级目录的 511 条目，
you know point is actually entry five eleven of the top level directory,
而现在只是 255 。
and it is only two five five.
有人知道为什么是这样吗？
Anybody any ideas why this is the case.
我们说过有一位，
We said that one bit
我们要用但其实没有使用的，
that we said we were gonna use we actually aren't using,
因为符号扩展问题，也是为了让它变得更容易，
because of sign extension problems is just makes it easier
并且我们不需要那么多内存。
and we also don't need that memory.
是的，这就是正确的答案，
Yeah, so that's exactly the right answer,
所以这是愚蠢的技术细节，
so this is basically stupid technicality,
所以虚拟地址原则上，
so the virtual addresses are in principle,
我觉得是 39 位，
I think 39 bits, right,
但是实际上在 xv6 中，只有 38 个，
and but we actually in xv6, only 38 of them,
因此，顶端的 MAXVA ，
and as a result, you know the top of the MAXVA for us,
它是 255 条目。
it is basically the 255 entry.
我们不使用 39 位的原因是，
And the reason we don't use the 39 bits,
没有特别好的理由，
is for no particular good reason,
基本上，如果你设置了第 39 位，
and then that basically if you have the thirty ninth bit set,
则 64 位地址中的所有剩余位必须为 1 。
then all the remaining bits in the 64 bit address have to be ones.
我们不想处理这个问题，
And so we just didn't want to deal with this problem
如果我们设置了 39 ，
that if we ever set 39,
我们也要设置 40 41 42 43 等，
we also have to set the forty forty first, forty second, forty third etc
直到 64 。
until the sixty fourth.
所以这是解释，能理解吗。
So that's an explanation, that makes sense.
嗯。
Yeah.
这是一个非常好的观察。
That's a very good observation though.
我也有一个问题，为什么文本和数据在同一页上。
So I also had a question about why is the text and data on the same page.
也是一个很好的问题。
Very good question, also.
这看起来很愚蠢，
That seems stupid right,
我的意思是为什么不把它们放在单独的页面上，
I mean why not put them on separate pages,
这样你才能更仔细地设置权限。
so that you can actually set the permission, that's more carefully.
主要原因是，
And the main reason,
我们这样做是为了简单。
we're doing that is for simplicity.
通常 exec 更复杂，
Usually make exec more complicated
我们想 exec 尽可能简单。
and we wanted the simplest exec possible.
真正的操作系统不会在同一页中包含数据和文本，
So a real operating system would not have data and text in the same page,
事实上，我们必须指定，
in fact we have to specify
如果你查看 makefile 中加载器标志，
that if you look at the loader flag in the makefile
你会看到，它有 -N 选项，
you'll see that it has the -N option
它强制数据和文本，
and that force is actually data and text
在一个连续的，而不是在单独的页面中。
to be in a contiguous not in separate pages.
关于这个，还有什么问题吗。
Any more questions about this.
我有一个后续问题，
I had a follow up question,
关于我们使用的位数。
regarding the number of bits, we're using.
你说我们只用了 38 位，
So you said we're using just 38 bits,
硬件仍然提供给我们使用 39 位，
is it is like the hardware still provides for us to use 39 bits,
但是我们设计操作系统使用 38 位。
but we are designing our operating system that we're using 38.
嗯。
Yeah.
所以我们，
So we're basically
如果机器有超过 2 的 38 次方的内存，
if the machine had more ram two to thirty eight,
我们就不能用那些内存了。
we would not be able to use that ram.
现在我们运行的，我们假设的，
Now we're running we're assuming
内存远少于 2 的 38 次方，
basically much less memory than two to thirty eight,
所以这对我们来说没什么影响。
so it's not a big deal for us.
但是如果是真正的操作系统，我们会做得更好。
But the real operating system, we would have done better.
所以，只是为了简单。
So just pure for simplicity.
我们想让你尽可能轻松，
We want to make it as easy for you as possible,
尽可能少阅读代码。
by reading a few lines of code possible.
好的。
Okay.
是的，理解了。
Yeah, makes sense.
好的，那么现在，让我们切换到第二部分。
Okay, so now, let's switch to part two.
让我们来看一张图片，
And so let's bring up, a picture,
你可能看了很多次。
you probably have looked at a lot.
内核地址空间，
The kernel address space right,
左边是虚拟地址空间，
on the left is virtual address space,
右边是物理内存，
on the right is physical memory,
你知道这里是 IO 设备，
you know here are IO devices,
从这里开始是 DRAM ，
and then from here on is you know DRAM,
直到 128 兆字节。
and you know and basically running into what actually one twenty 28 megabytes for us.
因为我们假设，
Because we just assume that
内存不超过 250（误） 128 兆字节。
there's no more than 250 and one twenty eight megabytes of memory.
所以这部分物理内存就是空闲内存。
And so this part of the physical memory is the free memory.
从那里开始，这是内核，
And then from that, this was kernel,
哎呀，我画错了。
oops, I drew a little bit wrong.
让我更小心一点，
Let me be more careful,
这里我们有内核文本和数据。
so, here we basically have kernel text and data.
然后上面的内存，就是内核分配器拥有的内存，
And then you know this memory above, basically memory that the kernel allocator has
从那里我们为用户程序分配内存，
and from there we allocate memory for user programs,
我们为页表等分配内存。
we allocate memory for pagetables, etc.
内核为它们分配所有，
Kernel allocates everything for them,
直到内存耗尽，
until it runs out of memory,
当它用完时，它会达到 128 兆字节，
when it runs out it gets to one twenty eight megabyte
然后它开始返回错误或系统调用。
and then it starts returning errors or system calls.
好的。
Okay.
好的，那么让我把第一部分做好，
Good, so let me pull off my first part correct,
从某种意义上说，这是任务的第二部分，
in some sense of this assignment it was part two of the assignment,
就是运行或者复制内核页表，
was just to run with or copy the kernel pagetables,
而且每个进程都有自己的内核页表。
and every process has its own kernel pagetables.
这就是这里的任务，
That was basically that's the assignment here,
所以让我进入代码，
so let me for jumping into the code,
让我实际看几件事，
let me actually see a couple things,
关于它的，更一般的事情。
more general things about it.
所以第二部分。
So part two.
也许你头脑中的第一个问题是，
And maybe the first question really to sort of get your head around is
在某些方面你做了一些微不足道的事，
like you know in some ways you do something trivial right,
我们已经有了内核页表，
we already have the kernel pagetable,
我们只需复制[]个副本，
we just have to make [] copies of it,
每个进程一个副本。
for one copy for each particular process.
你可能会说，这能有多难，
You, you might say well you know how hard can it be,
因为几个原因，这是有些难度的。
it turns out it was a little bit harder for a couple reasons.
一些好的原因，一些不太好的原因，
Some good ones, some less good ones,
它比看起来要难。
harder than it seems.
一个原因是，
And one reason is that
xv6 代码很特别，
you know xv6 code it's specialized,
针对一个内核页表。
for one kernel pagetable.
你在 kvminit 中看到的。
You know, you saw that in kvminit.
是的，所以这就有点一概而论，
Yeah, and so that makes it a little bit generalizing,
你知道这需要一些工作，
you know it's a little bit of work,
因为你必须修改 xv6 代码。
because you have to modify the xv6 code.
如你所见， kvminit 不是完全，
kvminit as you also saw is not the full,
为内核构建页表。
for building pagetable for the kernel.
也有一些在 procinit 中，
There's also stuff in procinit,
它添加映射到内核页表。
that actually adds mappings to the kernel pagetable.
甚至有一些在 virtio_disk 。
And there's even something in virtio_disk,
真正与内核页表进行交互。
the actually interacts, you know the kernel pagetable.
所以内核中没有唯一的地方，
So basically there's no one single place in the kernel,
用于构建内核页表。
where actually the kernel pagetable actually is built.
第三个原因，为什么这有些复杂，
Then the third reason, why you know this is slightly complicated,
因为你还得做清理工作。
because you also have to deal with cleanup.
因为有一个创建这些副本的方面，
So there's the aspect of actually creating these copies,
所以每次用户进程退出时，
but when every time user process exit,
我们还要清理那些使用过的页表，
we also have to clean up those pagetables that were in use,
因为我们希望将它们放回到空闲内存池中，
because we want to return them to the pool of free memory,
好让我们以后可以使用它们，
so that we can use them later,
以便我们可以继续运行进程。
so that we can keep on running processes.
这就是那里发生的事情。
That's what happens there.
这让事情变得有些复杂，
And that makes things a little bit complicated,
因为我们必须要小心，
because we've got to be little careful,
在释放内核页表
in actually freeing the kernel pagetable
或内核页表的副本时，
or copy of the kernel pagetable,
我们当然不想
but we certainly don't want to,
释放仍在使用中的内存，
you know, free memory that actually still in use,
或别的页表仍在使用的页表条目。
or page table entries are still used by other pagetables.
所以我们得小心，
So we gotta be careful there,
然后，你知道，很容易出现错误。
and then, you know basically, it's easy to make a small error.
当你复制那些页表时。
You know pagetable, when your copy those pagetables.
如果你[得到]一点东西，
You know if you get a little thing,
你会得到一个很难的 bug 。
you know basically you get a hard hard bug.
这里的一个问题是，我之前说过，
And one of the problems here is I said earlier is,
困难的 bug 出现的时间要晚得多。
the hard bug shows up much much later.
你已经构建了内核页表，
You've built the kernel pagetable,
构建了内核页表的副本，
are built copy of the kernel pagetable,
一切看起来都很好，你装入 satp 寄存器，
all looks fine, you load loaded in satp,
甚至内核会运行一小段时间，然后才死机。
they may even maybe the kernel runs for a little while, and then panics.
结果发现死机的原因，
And it turns out you know the reason that panics,
因为你在页表中犯了个小错误，
because you made some small mistake in the pagetable,
在很久很久以前。
long, long time ago.
所以这就是为什么
And so this is one reason why
它会让内核编程很困难。
it makes you know makes life difficult for kernel programming.
你知道，这些困难的 bug ，
And you know and basically these hard bugs,
基本上都很费时间去追踪。
basically are just time consuming to track down.
因为发生的时候，
Because of the point that you know happens,
其实不是 bug 的真正原因，
that's actually not the real cause of of the bug,
但是真正的原因，
but about you know the real cause,
是你之前设置页表时的某个地方。
you know somewhere way earlier when you set up the pagetables.
好的。
Okay, um.
所以结果是，
So it turns out,
有两种方法解决这个问题，
there are two approaches to go about it,
你知道，这个实验可以采用两种解决方案。
you know to this lab which sort of two solution approaches.
事实上，你们中的一些人可能混合使用它们，
In fact, some of you have probably used a mixture of them,
第一个方法是 copy 方法。
the one you know approach what call copy approach.
copy 方法从字面上复制内核页表，
And the copy approach basically literally makes a copy to the kernel pagetable,
所以每次你都需要一个新的内核页表，
so every time you need a new kernel pagetable,
你为页表分配页面，
you allocate pages for the pagetable,
你为它们填充数据，等等。
you fill them in etc, etc.
还有一种方法，第二种方法是，
And there's, that's one approach, the second approach is
共享内核页表，
basically to share the kernel pagetable,
在这种情况下，你要做的是
and in this case, what you do is
不是创建一个内核页表的干净副本，
instead of trying to make a literally nice clean copy of the kernel pagetables,
而是共享不会修改的所有条目。
you share all the entries that are basically are going to be unmodified.
你从任务中知道，
You know from the assignment,
基本上从 CLINT 到 PLIC 地址以上的任何内容，
that basically anything above CLINT to PLIC address,
实际上是不变的，
is actually going to be unchanged, unmodified,
那里没有你要加载的东西。
there's nothing you have to load there.
在第三部分，
In the part three,
你知道，基本上，
so you know what are basically,
从零开始的所有条目可能是相同的，
all the entries from above zero are probably identical,
所以你可以分享这些条目。
so you could share those entries, if you will.
这两种方法都很好。
So that both approaches are actually perfectly fine.
没有明确的，哪一个更好。
It's not abundantly clear, which one is the better one.
我的解决方案，采取这种方法（共享方法）。
My solution, take this approach.
我没有很好的理由，
And I don't really have great justification for it
除了可能部分原因是可以偷懒。
other than maybe partially laziness.
我不想想太多，
I didn't want to think too hard,
内核页表中有什么，
what's in the kernel pagetable,
所以我想出所有东西保持不变，
and so I figured out all the things that are going to stay the same,
为什么复制它们，
why do you copy them over
或者复制 pte ，
or you know copy the ptes over
然后我不得不认真考虑，
and then I have to think too hard about
这实际上不是内核地址空间的一部分。
actually isn't that part of the kernel address space.
这会导致更少代码，
And you know leads to short code,
但是我不确定，
but you know I'm not sure actually
比复制解决方案更少。
shorter than, for example, the copy solution.
但重要的是要认识到，
But it's important to realize that basically
有两种不同的方法来解决这个特定问题。
there are two different ways of going about this particular problem.
在这两种情况下，无论你用什么方法，
In either case, you know whatever approach you use,
都有某种实施策略。
you know there's sort of an implementation strategy to it.
你知道我使用的实施策略，
And you know the implementation strategy that I use
对于几乎任何内核程序，
for almost any kernel program
都是按部就班地做所有事情。
is to do everything in baby steps.
所以我可能，在我的脑海里有一个总的计划，
So I might have, for general plan in my head
关于我是如何从头走到尾的，
about how I go over the whole,
我要做的所有改变，
you know all the changes I want to make,
但是一旦我开始做这些改变，
but once I start making these changes,
我先做一两个，
I do like one or two,
然后确保它们起作用，
and then make sure that those work first
然后继续往前走，
and then you know, keep going,
我做的另一件事是，
and the other thing I do
主要是保留现有代码，
is mostly used as a strategy to keep the existing code,
不是修改最初的代码，
don't really modify certainly not initially,
我是添加代码，并切换到新代码，
I just add code and switch to this new code
然后[按部就班]，
and then the little baby steps
我这么做的原因是，
and the reason I'm doing that is
我可以很容易地比较新旧代码，
that I can easily compare old new code,
我总是有一个有效的旧解决方案，
and I always have a working old solution,
我可以直接回到过去，
that I can just roll back to,
如果发生了一些奇怪的错误，
so in case some strange bugs happens,
然后我可以后退一步，然后再试一次，
then I can go back maybe one step and then try again,
所以就像我说的，那样知道我的推理是错的。
so you figure out like I said were my reason was wrong.
小步走，部分原因是，
Basically you know baby steps what partly
这些 bug 太难追踪了。
because these bugs are so hard to track down.
好的，让我切换到代码，
Okay, let me switch to code,
从 vm.c 开始。
so maybe starting vm.c.
这是现有的 kvminit ，
So, the, here's the existing kvminit,
每个人都可以看到代码吗？
and actually can everybody see the code?
好的，任务要求我们
Okay, and, the assignment we are asked
对它（内核页表）做一个副本，
for correct is to make a copy of it
我做的方式是，
and the way I do that is,
让我看看在哪里。
let me see where that is.
这是我的 uvmcreate ，
So here's my uvmcreate,
那只是无聊的部分，
that's just boring part,
基本上就是创建分配顶级页目录，
that's basically creating, allocating the top level page directory,
还有 l2 页目录。
also the l2 page directory.
然后这里是我的 kvm- ，
And then here's my kvm,
相当于 kvminit 。
the equivalent of kvminit.
我在这里获得了顶部的页目录，
So I get the top of the page directory here,
在这个位置。
in this site.
然后，我会复制从内核页表前 511 个条目，
Then, basically I copy the top 511 entries from the kernel pagetable
它已经由 kvminit 设置好，
that was already set up by kvminit,
这给了我大部分的内核页表。
and so that gives me most of the kernel pagetable.
然后，我需要映射所有设备，
And then, I just have to map in all the devices
它们在这里 0 号条目。
that live in the zero entry,
因为 0 号条目，我们稍后要修改它，
because zero entry, the entry that we're going to modify it later
或者我们会将用户页面映射到底部。
or we're going to map user pages into the bottom.
有几个设备在 0 号条目中，
And there's a couple devices that live in that in zero entry,
那些的设备需要添加到，
those you know device needs to be added to the to this,
每个进程的内核页表。
per process pagetable, kernel page table.
所以我回到前面的这张图片上。
And so maybe I go back to this picture earlier.
让我再次设置内核页表，
So let me put up the kernel pagetable again,
可能这张图片跟任何都一样，
maybe this picture as good as any,
所以如果你考虑我的解决方案，
so if you think about my solution,
基本上这些条目我只是与现有内核页表共享，
basically these entries I just share with existing kernel pagetable,
所以我不需要分配任何 l1 或 l2 或 l0 级别，
so I don't have to allocate any l1 or l2 or l0 levels,
它们已经存在了，
they already exists
我唯一做的就是字面意思上的复制 pte 条目。
and the only thing I do is basically literally copy pte entry.
所以只有底部部分或底部条目，
So only the bottom part or the bottom entry that is the piece,
我需要真正重建或复制，而不只是复制 pte 。
I need to actually rebuild or copy explicitly instead of copying ptes.
这就覆盖了底部的 1G 字节的地址空间。
And that covers you know the bottom one gigabyte address space.
在一页中包含 4096 。
In one page covers 4096.
所以这个条目包含 512 。
And so this you know this entry covers five twelve.
这（最右边的）是 2 兆字节了。
But this has been two megabyte.
而这（中间的）是一千兆字节，
And this is one gigabyte
所以只有一个条目，我需要填充它。
and basically only one of these entries, I need to fill it.
能理解吗?
That makes sense?
回到我的代码，基本上，
So returning to my code and basically,
这就是我所做的一切， kvmcreate 。
that's all I do, kvmcreate.
在我的 kvmfree 中是清理方案，
And in kv- my kvmfree is maybe not, maybe clean solution,
但我充分利用了这些知识，
but I take full advantage of the knowledge
我不需要对条目 1 到 511 做任何事情，
that I don't have to do anything from the entries one to 511
在顶级页目录中。
in the top page level directory.
唯一要处理的条目是
The only entry to do anything about is
内核顶级目录的底部条目。
the bottom entry of the kernel of the top level directory.
它指向一个 l1 条目，
That points to one l1 entry
那个 l1 条目，我只需要遍历，
and that one l1 entry, I just need to go through
释放旧的 l2 或 l0 条目。
and free old l2 or l0 entries.
然后，释放 l1 ，
And then the ends you know free l1
然后是内核页表。
and then the kernel pagetable.
这就是我的 kvmfree 和 kvmcreate 。
And so that's my k- kvmfree and my kvmcreate.
这样我就可以创建内核页表进程，
So that allows me to create a kernel pagetable process
然后在使用完成后释放。
and then free once is when we're done.
抱歉，提个小问题。
Sorry, quick question.
您能再解释一下，
Could you explain again,
为什么只使用 1 到 512 而不使用 0 ？
the reasoning for only using one to five twelve and not zero?
是。
Yes.
好的，那么，
Okay, so,
也许最容易的是，让我回到这里的图片。
maybe the easy thing to do actually let me go back through the picture here.
所以我们有一个内核地址空间。
So we have a kernel address space, correct.
这个 Ox8000 等等，
And you know this O x eight zero zero zero zero blah blah blah,
在，嗯。
in, um.
在顶层页面目录中， Ox0 属于哪个条目。
What entry does O x zero fall into in the for the top level page directory.
比如。
It's like, the.
0 号条目？
Zeroth entry?
不，不是 0 号条目。
No, not to zeroth entry, right.
所以你知道 0 号条目，
So whatever you know what zero entry like this entry,
这个条目包含多少？
how much does it cover this entry.
多少地址空间，
How much address space,
顶层页面目录的底部条目即 0 号条目包含多少。
does this bottom entry of the zero entry of the top level page directory cover.
我认为 CLINT 是
I think CLINT is,
在 0 到 0x2000 之间。
it's free between zero and 0x2000.
是的，也许我会这么做，
Yeah, so okay so maybe I'm going to,
我认为你的方向是正确的，
I think you're absolutely right direction,
所以最下面的条目复制了一千兆字节。
so the bottom entry copy one gigabyte, right.
我们知道，也许我可以。
And we know like maybe I can.
我们看到最下面的条目是一千兆字节，
We saw the bottom entry one gigabyte which,
在那一千兆字节有 CLINT 和 PLIC ，
in that one gigabyte just CLINT the PLIC, right,
我相信还有 UART 和 VIRTIO_disk 。
UART and VIRTIO_disk, I believe.
然后 KERNBASE 位于一个更高的条目上。
And then KERNBASE actually already sits up in a higher entry, right.
我们可以计算一下，
We can compute if we wanted to,
我们可以取 0x80- ，
we could take 0x eight zero correct,
移位 12 ，移位 9 ，移位 9 ，
shifted twelve, shift nine, shift nine,
我想，我不记得顶部是什么了。
and I I think I don't remember the top we have what is.
试着弄清楚，也许我们来试一试。
Try to figure it out, if you want to actually maybe we'll try.
在演讲中这样做总是有[风险]的，
This is always very risky to do in lecture,
所以， gdb 。
but, so, gdb.
我们来看看 memlayout.h ，这是 KERNBASE ，
So let's go to layout, here's KERNBASE,
所以我们可以打印。
so we could print.
移位是 12 ，这给了我们，偏移量。
So shift is twelve, that gives us, that offset.
哎呀。
Oops.
好的，然后我们移位这个值。
Good as that, so then we'll shift that guy.
我想你可以看到这个。
I think you could see this.
九。
Nine.
现在再做一次，
Right now is the next entry one more,
所以这是条目 2 。
so this entry two.
能理解吗。
Does it make sense.
所以我们回到这里来看图片。
So we go back to our picture here.
KERNBASE 是条目 2 ，
Basically KERNBASE is entry two,
在顶级页目录中。
in the top of page directory, right.
我们从作业的第三部分了解到，
So and we know from the third part of the assignment,
我们不需要考虑 PLIC 上面的任何东西。
basically we don't really have to worry about anything above PLIC.
所有这些东西上都在条目 0 。
And all that stuff falls actually entry zero.
好的?
Okay?
所以这回答了之前的问题。
So that answer the earlier question.
好的，谢谢。
Yes, thank you.
好的，现在我们要做的还剩下的就是，
Okay, so now we the only thing we have left to do is,
再次检查调用函数 kvmcreate 的地方，
you know, double check where we got to call this function kvmcreate,
这将是 allocproc 。
and and you know that's going to be allocproc.
所以，并且。
So, and.
哎呀。
Oops.
这里是新进程初始化的地方，
Here where is the new process initialized,
我相信你们都是一样的，
then you know I'm sure all of you is exactly the same way,
当你在 proc 结构中声明字段时，
you entry, you allocate when you declare field in the proc structure
它的结果，我们放在内核页表中。
and basically the result of it is actually what we stick in the kernel pagetable.
好的，我们需要考虑的另一件事是，
Okay, then we only the thing that we have to worry about,
当然我们需要使用页表，
of course we need to use the pagetable,
所以，我们需要查看调度器。
and so we need to look at the scheduler.
基本上，任务多少会告诉你做什么，
Basically, the assignment more or less told you what to do
在切换到用户进程之前，
which is you know before you switch to that user process,
你需要切换内核页表，
you need to switch the kernel pagetables,
意味着加载进程内核页表到 satp 。
which basically means loading, you know, this process kernel pagetable in satp.
然后当你完成切换来运行另一个进程，
And then when you're done switching in running the other process,
你从另一个进程返回，
you come back from running the other process
然后你回到并运行调度程序，
and you're gonna go back and run the scheduler,
你必须切换回主内核页表，
you gotta switch back to the main kernel pagetable,
[]内核页表，
the [] kernel pagetable,
因为这才是调度器实际使用的。
because that's the one that actually used by scheduler.
为什么我们做这个切换，
And why do we need to do this switch,
为什么这很重要。
why is this important.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
因为它选择了正确的内核页表，
So it picks the right kernel pagetable,
因为 satp ，当你转到页表条目时，
because the satp, when you go to the pagetable entries,
它选择了，
it picks the right,
它选择了正确的页表。
it picks the right pagetable to pick from.
嗯，稍等一下。
Yeah, hold on or something more than a second.
是的，所以好的，当我们停下来的时候。
Yeah, so okay, so when we stop.
好的，让我换一种方式问这个问题，
Okay, let me another way to ask this question,
这个内核页表是什么时候释放的。
when is this kernel pagetable freed.
当用户进程完成时，
When the user process is done,
所以如果我们不交换（页表），
so if we didn't switch,
那就意味着，
that would mean that that,
我们可以使用一个被释放进程的页表，
we could be using a pagetable of a process that was being freed,
页表被释放了，
so the pagetable was freed,
所以，我们不想依赖于当前未运行的进程。
so we don't want to be dependent on the process were not running right now.
没错，我们永远不能释放当前正在运行的进程的页表。
Yeah, exactly, we can never free the page table of the process that's currently running.
所以我们要有一个计划，
So we have to have some plan,
在进程不再运行时释放它们。
you know to actually free process at the point that they're not running anymore.
wait 系统调用是我们的退出方式，
And you know the wait system call is our way out,
wait 系统调用查看有没有子进程，
basically wait calls look if there's any children
决定是不是可以清理。
that are are not you know that can be cleaned up.
然后把它们清理掉。
And then they cleans them up.
也就是说，
And that means that basically,
当父进程切换进程时，
when the parent process switch over process,
我们必须保证，
we're going to make absolutely sure that you know that,
satp 寄存器中加载的页表，
the pagetable that is loaded in the satp register,
不是，
is not you know one of the,
不是那个将要释放的进程页表。
is not that process you know pagetable will actually currently free.
也可能根本没有进程在运行，
You know it could be the case there's no process running at all right
所以调度器有它自己的页表，
and so the scheduler basically has its own pagetable,
所以，所有进程都可以被清理。
sort of all processes can actually be cleaned up.
能理解吗？
That makes sense?
抱歉，我有个问题，
I'm sorry, I had a question,
你是不是把 CLINT 映射到
is it that you're mapping the C L I N T
新的进程内核页表中了？
into the new process kernel pagetables?
为什么？
Why?
因为任务说的我只需要，
Because I think the assignment says like I only have to,
用户进程不会比 CLINT 更大，好像是的。
user process, you will not be bigger than CLINT is that it.
当我映射 PLIC 和 CLINT 时，
When I map both the PLIC and the CLINT, right,
我认为任务告诉我们，
and so but I think the assignment told us that,
什么是最低的那个。
so what is the lowest one.
我想 PLIC 是最低的那个，
I think there PLIC is the lowest one,
这告诉我们，
and this [] told us,
用户进程不会大于 PLIC 地址。
that the user process will not be bigger than the PLIC address.
好的。
Okay.
只是为了简单，
Just to make it easy,
我们可以，
we could then,
想让它对你来说尽可能简单，
want to make it as easy as possible for you
当然，你愿意的话，可以做得更好。
clear you could have done a better if you wanted to.
但是，你知道这是最简单的事情。
But you know that was the simplest thing to do.
所以，你需要做一些修改才能让它正常工作。
So you have to make a few modifications to get it to work.
还有什么问题吗？
Any further questions?
我有一个问题，
I have a question,
能不能复制 0 到 512 ，
is it possible that you can copy zero to five twelve
然后每次切换时，
and then every time you switch,
仍在使用，比如全局根页表，
so you're still using like the global root pagetable
除了复制第一个根页表，
except you only copy the first root page table,
每次切换进程时，
and every time you switch a process,
都复制用户地址到。
you copy over the user's addresses over to.
是的。
Yeah.
能不能这么做。
Is that possible to do.
理论上，我认为你可以这样做，
In principle I think you could do something like that,
所以，不是分配一个进程，再释放它，
so instead of basically doing when you allocate a process and free it,
你可以在调度程序切换期间动态执行。
you could do to dynamically during this scheduler switch.
嗯，看起来很复杂。
Um, seems complicated.
那可能花费更多，
That might be more costly,
因为，这意味着每次在两个进程之间切换时，
because that means that every time you switch between two processes,
你可能必须复制内核页表的一部分。
you may have to make a copy of parts of the kernel pagetable.
所以这可能对性能有影响，
And so that might be turn to perform,
不是一件理想的事情。
it's not an ideal thing.
任务没有说任何关于它的事，
The assignment didn't really say anything about it,
如果你这样做了，它可能在 usertests 中超时。
you might have timed out in usertests, if you did that.
是的，我只是想知道，
Yeah I was just wondering,
因为我试过那个方法，
because I tried that approach,
这是一次糟糕的经历，
and it was a bad experience,
我想知道这是否可行。
I was wondering if that was possible.
我可以想象的到，但是我认为理论上是可行的，
I can imagine, but I I think it's in principle possible,
你可以每次分配新的页表并切换，
you could allocate a new page table correctly and switch every time,
并在切换出来的时候释放它。
and free it when you switch out.
我不认为这很简单，
I don't think it's simple,
但是，你知道，我认为理论上是可行的。
but you know in principle it's possible I think.
可能对 xv6 做一些其他修改。
Perhaps some other modifications to xv6.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
当然另一个改变是，
Of course the other change that,
必须要改的是 usertrapret ，
of course have to make is usertrapret,
你必须确保，
you got to make sure that
你使用进程内核页表运行。{}进程内核页表。
actually you run with the the processes kernel page table.
好的？
Okay?
好的，那我们切换到，
Okay, so let's switch them to,
第三部分。
I guess part three.
切换回这里。
To switch back to actually here.
好的，那么，
Okay, so,
这可能不是一张有帮助的图片。
actually that's maybe not a helpful picture.
好的，第三部分。
Okay, part three.
所以基本上我们的计划是，
So basically what our plan is,
我们有像之前一样的内核页表，
we have our kernel pagetable as before,
我们有 PLIC 条目在某个地方。
and you know we have the PLIC entry sitting somewhere.
我们要做的是，
And what we're gonna do is,
我们将使用 PLIC 下面的所有东西，
we're gonna use you know everything below PLIC,
来保存用户页表，
to actually store the user pagetable,
我们将把用户页表映射到所有的用户程序中，
we're going to map the user pagetable into all the user program,
用户程序实际上在内核页表中，
the user program actually in the kernel pagetable,
在底部。
in the bottom.
这就是我们的目标，
And that's the goal,
第一个要问的问题是，
and what's the first question to ask,
为什么[]要这么做。
you know why the [] do that.
这样有什么好处吗，
Is there any you know any advantage of it
我觉得可能，
and you know I think maybe the,
这可能是一种简单的方式
it may be a easy way
来理解为什么它很有趣，
to see why it might be interesting
是[]与 copyin 比较。
is to [] compare to copyin.
新 copyin 和旧 copyin 。
The new copyin and the old copyin.
所以，如果， copyin 发生了什么，
So, if you know what happens in the copyin,
copyin 将数据从用户空间复制到内核地址空间。
it correctly, copyin copies data from the user space into the kernel address space.
但是如果内核没有用户地址映射。
Um, and but you know if the kernel has does not have the user address map,
内核必须在这时分配这个页，
basically the kernel has to do this page the time, correct,
因为虚拟地址空间中的页面可以是连续的，
because the pages in virtual address space may be continuous
尽管对于物理地址空间，它们不是连续的。
with the physical address space, they're not continuous.
内核在 copyin 上所做的，
And basically with the kernel does in copyin,
将虚拟用户地址转换为物理地址。
it basically translates the virtual user address into physical address.
由于内核具有所有物理内存映射，
Since the kernel has all physical memory mapped with identity mapping,
物理地址[也是]有效的内核虚拟地址，
the physical address is also a valid kernel virtual address
然后它移动那一页的部分，
and then it basically moves whatever part of that page,
那些需要复制的物理页。
physical page needs to be copied that actually copies it.
如果某个数据结构，
And so if data structure,
跨越两个个页面边界，
for example spans, you know, two page boundary,
比如，在实验 2 中使用的 sysinfo 结构，
like for example, the sysinfo struct may be used in lab two,
可能跨越页表边界，
maybe spans a pagetable boundary,
它会复制，比如可能是，
it will copy like maybe you know
第一个物理页的一些字节，
some bytes from the first physical page
然后是第二物理页的一些字节。
and then some bytes from the second physical page.
这个能理解吗。
Does it make sense.
这就是内核 copyin 所做的，
That's what the kernel copyin does,
目标是让它们使用新的 copyin ，
and the goal was basically to get them into a new copyin,
使内核程序不必担心物理布局，
where the kernel program didn't really have to worry about the physical layout,
不占用用户地址空间。
basically off the user address space.
这个新 copyin ，
And this new copyin,
我们可以看到基本上什么都不做，
you know we see we basically do nothing,
没有其他东西，只是复制，
literally nothing else, just copy,
从用户地址直接到内核。
do, you know, from the user addresses straight into the kernel.
而且我们也不再需要调用 walk 了，
And we don't really have to call walk anymore,
因为我们可以依赖，
because we can rely on the,
我们正确设置页表，
we set up that the pagetables correctly,
现在，页表硬件将为我们做 walk 。
now the pagetable hardware will do the walk for us.
是的。
Right.
这就是我们的目标，
And so that was the goal,
所以这让内核程序员的生活更轻松一点，
and so that makes life of kernel programmers are a little bit easier,
这种方法还有没有别的优点。
on any other advantages to this approach.
是不是性能也更好，
Is it also more performance,
因为硬件来做 walk 而不是软件。
because the hardware is gonna do the walking and not software.
是啊，一个方法，
Yeah, one way to,
我认为肯定有性能的提高，
I think their performance implications for sure,
考虑这个的一种方式是，
one way to think about this is that
在 copyin 中，如果内核数据结构
in copyin correct, if the kernel data structure
或者我们从用户空间复制到内核空间的数据比较大，
or data data that we copied from user space to kernel spaces big,
我们必须这样做，一次一页，
we have to do that you know page at a time, right,
在每个页面中，我们都必须调用函数 walkaddr ，
in every page, we have to call this function walkaddr,
然后是内部的 walk 。
and then there's the internal walking.
所以，这可能是一个昂贵的花费。
And so, this might actually be a reasonable expenses expensive.
有什么例子，
What examples are there examples of
是内核从用户空间复制大量数据。
where the kernel copies a lot of data from user space.
哪个系统调用可能会从用户空间复制大量数据。
Which system call might copy a ton of data from user space.
write?
Write?
是的， write ，你说得对，
Yeah write, write, you're right,
你可以给出任意大小的任意缓冲区。
you can give an arbitrary, an arbitrary buffer of arbitrary size.
内核可能将其复制到，
And you know the kernel [] may have to copy this into,
文件系统或管道中。或者放进管子里。
for example, the file system or into a pipe.
这是很昂贵的。
And that could be a reasonable expensive.
你想想还有什么好处，
You gotta think what is another advantage,
如果用户，
if the user,
我们在任务中没有研究这个，
we didn't explore that in this assignment,
应该还有别的优点。
we should we could have one another advantage.
所以如果你想一想，
So if you think about,
这里的其中一些代码，
some of these, this code here correct,
当它把结构移出用户空间，
when it takes a structure out of user space,
它将整个结构复制到内核空间。
it copies the whole structure into kernel space.
如果用户空间被映射到内核页表，
If user space is mapped into the kernel pagetable,
我们也一定要这么做吗。
do we have to do that.
比如，如果我们需要更新结构体中的一个字段。
For example, if we have to update one field of the structure.
如果数据结构只是映射到内核地址空间，
So if data structure is just mapped into the kernel address space right,
那么我们可以读写，
then we can usually read and write,
通过 store 指令到特定的数据结构，
you know with store instruction through that particular data structure,
我们可以更新一个字段。
we can use update one field.
与现在内核做的不同，
Unlike the kernel now does,
它将结构体从内核空间复制到用户空间，
basically it copies the structure from kernel space to user space,
然后可能再使用 copyout 退出。
and then maybe back out using copyout.
因此，我们将用户空间映射到，
And so we map the user space into,
将用户程序映射到内核地址空间，
the user program into the kernel address space,
我们可以更自由地操纵它，
we can just manipulate it much more freely
而不是我们现在的做法。
than the way we do it now.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense,
就动机而言，为什么许多内核都有这种特殊的结构，
in terms of motivation, why many kernels actually have this particular structure
映射底部是用户，
where they map bottom part of the user,
将用户程序映射到内核地址空间的底部。
were to map the user program into the bottom part of the kernel address space.
好的？
Okay?
好的，让我们看我的代码，
Okay, so so let's see, look at my code
好让你明白实际是什么。
and and so you understand what actually.
我想有一个函数是关键，
I I guess so there's basically one function, that is the key,
假设我们正在建立有效的用户页表 ，
you know assume we were building somewhere valid user pagetable,
然后我们需要将
and then we just have to
条目从用户页表映射到内核页表，
map entries from the user pagetable into the kernel pagetable,
进程内核页表，
the processes kernel pagetables,
函数 kvmmapuser 就是这样做的。
that function kvmmapuser exactly does this.
这挺枯燥的，
And it's pretty boring,
工作中主要的几个点是，
the main couple interesting points to point out in work,
是的，那是与 uvmalloc 同样类型的接口，
yeah yeah that's the same sort of interfaces to uvmalloc whatever
或者如果，
or basically if you know
你从旧尺寸页面转到新尺寸页面。
you go from the old size up to the new size page at a time.
嗯。
Yeah.
你找到 upte ，
You find the upte,
指向特定虚拟地址的 pte 的指针，
you know the pointer to the pte for that particular virtual address
在用户页表中。
in the user page table.
所以我们来看一下，
And so we look at the,
如果你看这张图片，
if you look at the picture
我们有一段时间了，
that we had a little while back,
看这张图片。
you know look at this picture.
这将返回的是，
Basically, what this is going to return correct is,
我们遍历用户页表，
we're going to walk the user pagetable
我们找到 upte ，
and we'll find for example the upte
它映射到特定虚拟地址，
that maps in that particular virtual address
那个地址指向页表中的那个条目。
where we basically pointer to that entry into the pagetable,
这就是 walk 所做的。
and that's what walk does.
如果这个东西映射了，它不是零，
And so if thing is mapped, it's not
那一定意味着，至少答案是，
that must mean at least the answer is
检查映射是否在那里。
just to check, double check that actually the map is there.
我们检查这是有效的，
We check this valid,
这在某种意义上有帮助调试，
there's debugging help in some sense,
你知道我们应该在有效的情况下。
you know we should be the case that is valid.
然后我在内核页表中做同样的事情，
And then I do the same thing in the kernel pagetable,
我还查看进程内核页表中的虚拟地址，
I look up that virtual address also in the process of kernel pagetable,
但这一次我调用 walk 带上 1 ，
but I call this time walk with one,
因此，如果需要，它会分配中间页。
so it actually allocates intermediate pages if necessary.
然后，我得到指向内核 pte 的指针，
Then once I got the pointer to the kernel pte,
我只是将用户 pte 复制到内核 pte 。
I just copy the user pte into the kernel pte.
可能你们中的很多人调用了 mappages 。
So probably a lot of you called mappages.
但我是直接将 pte 复制到内核 pte 中，
But I just copied directly the pte into the kernel pte
当然，我要禁用一些位，
and of course I gotta disable some bits
稍后我们会讲到，
which we'll talk about in a second,
但是，它的实质是，
but, the essence of it is,
我只是复制内核页面 pte 条目。
I just copy the kernel page pte entries.
这意味着，
And so that means that,
用户程序的物理内存是共享的，
for example the physical memory for the user program is shared,
在内核空间和用户空间之间。
between kernel space and user space.
好的，能理解吗。
Okay, does that make sense.
好的，切换一些位，
Okay, so in terms of switching up some bits
比需要的多一点，
a little bit more than necessary,
我关闭了执行位，
but I switch off the execute bit,
我关闭了写入位，
I I switch off the write bit,
因为 copyin 只需要读取，不需要写入，
is copyin only needs to read never writes to it
copyout 也是这样。
or copyout does that.
然后，你也必须切换 u 标志位。
And then, you have to switch up u bit.
这是一种 RISC-V 特定的东西，
And that is a sort of RISC-V specific thing,
如果你在内核模式下运行，
that if you're running in kernel mode,
并且你在 pte 条目中设置了 u 标志位，
and you've been u bit is set in the pte entry,
内核就不能访问那个特定页面。
the kernel can actually not access that particular page.
事实上，你可以，
In fact you can,
这是一个选择，
this is almost a choice,
你还可以对 RISC-V 硬件进行编程，
you can also actually program the RISC-V hardware,
这处于内核模式，并忽略 u 标志位。
that basically in kernel mode and ignores the u bit.
但是 xv6 没有做这一点，
And um, but xv6 doesn't do that,
所以你必须切换 u 标志位。
so you have to switch up the u bit.
有关于 u 标志位的问题吗，
Any questions about the u bit,
因为有很多人人问到了它。
because the required number of you asked about it.
那么这么做只是为了确保，
So is this done just to make sure
内核不会对用户内存做什么坏事。
that the kernel doesn't do anything bad to user memory.
是的，那么为什么会这样？
Yeah, so why is this the case why is this,
所以问题是，这是出于调试的原因，
you know, so the question is like is this for debugging reasons,
还是有某种隔离的原因这样做。
or is there sort of isolation reasons to do so.
我想这主要是出于调试的原因。
And, I think this is mostly for debugging reasons.
因为内核反正是完全控制的，
Because the kernel is in full control anyway, right,
内核可以修改 satp 寄存器，
kernel can change the satp register,
它页可以禁用分页，
as well it can disable paging as it wants to,
所以不是，保护用户空间不受内核影响，
so it's not like you know the user space is protected from the kernel,
我认为主要是为了帮助内核开发，
I think it's mostly to basically help kernel development,
从 xv6 来说，
for example xv6 case correct,
未修改的 xv6 不应该引用用户页面。
unmodified xv6 should never be reference user page period.
还有，你知道，
Um, and um, and so that you know,
如果你这样做，会有所帮助，
and basically this just helps if you happen to do
出现意外，你会立即得到页面错误，
that by accident anyway you would get immediately page fault
内核错误，
and you know a kernel panic
这将有助于内核调试，
and it will help the kernel debug,
开发人员调试内核。
developer to debug the kernel.
能理解吗。
Does that makes sense.
是的，谢谢。
Yeah, thank you.
我有一个后续的问题，
I have a follow up question to that,
我理解了关于用户位的部分，
I think the part about the user bit makes sense,
但是关于写入和执行位是怎样的？
but what about the write and execute bits.
是的。
Yeah.
执行位必须打开吗？
So does the execute bit have to be on?
内核用这个页面做什么？
What does the kernel do with this page?
它只是读，
The only read from, right,
唯一的事情，唯一的指令，
the only thing the only instruction
是从这个页面获取数据，
that basically grabs data from this pages,
memmove 指令和 copyin 。
memmove instruction and copyin.
所以它只执行加载指令，
So it only it does execute load instructions from it,
或者从特定页面加载值，
or loads values from that particular page
并且页面应该只包含数据。
and the page should only contain data.
所以内核没有理由写入该页，
And so there's no reason that the kernel should be writing to that page
所以出于保守考虑，
and so it has to be conservative,
我禁用了写入位。
I disabled the write bit.
并且不应该从该页面执行指令，
And there should be confirmed never executed instruction from that page,
所以我也禁用了执行位。
so I disable the execute bit too.
再说一次，我认为这主要是出于调试的原因，
Again, this is mostly I think for debugging reasons,
而不是因为隔离的原因。
not for isolation reasons.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
OK, makes sense, thanks.
好的，那么现在我们唯一需要做的是，
Okay, so now the only thing we need to do,
基本上有一些位置，
is basically there's a bunch of places
这个代码，这个调用函数在什么位置。
where this code is being where this function is being called.
我们看看这些调用的位置，
And we need to look at these places where call
了解发生了什么，
to understand what's going on,
或者怎么使用，
or how to use,
我想其中一个有趣的是，
and I think maybe one of the interesting ones
你们中很少人问到，
that you know numbers of you asked about
就是 fork 。
is fork.
确切地说，我们讨论他们两个。
And exactly we talk about both of them.
第一个 fork ，
The first fork,
这里是对 fork 的调用，
so here's call to fork
或者调用 fork 中的 kvmmapuser 。
or to call to kvmmapuser in fork.
它接受 n- ，
And it takes the n-,
我想大部分人问的主要问题是，
so the main question I think the most of you ask is,
为什么一定要是新的进程内核页表，
why does it have to be the new process kernel pagetable,
为什么必须从新进程复制页表，
why does it have to copy from the new process pagetable
而不是当前进程页表，
instead of from maybe the current process pagetable,
因为不管怎样，之后都是一样的，
because it's anyway an identical going forward,
基本上，它就是复制了，
basically does it just replicates the,
页表中的用户部分，
user part of the pagetable
那么为什么不使用当前页表来做这件事呢。
and so why can't we use the current pagetable for doing that.
为什么会出现这种情况，
Why actually turns out the case,
你必须用新的，
you actually have to use the new,
子进程的的用户页表。
you know the child's user part of the child user pagetable.
为什么会这样呢？
Why is that the case.
想一下你得到了什么 bug 。
Move you note what bug you get.
当你得到 remap 错误时。
When you get a remap error.
也许不是 remap 错误，可能是那个，
You go, maybe not remap error maybe that too,
但我想的不是 remap 的那个。
but I'm thinking of is not the remap one.
你们中的一些人试过，
Number of you tried it out,
你们感觉怎么样？
what was your personal experience.
线上有人试过吗？
Anybody on the call who tried this out?
我记得它们[导致的经历]，
I remember what they resulting experiences,
我觉得这个经历，我没有这个 bug ，
I think the resulting and I did not have the bug with,
我认为体验是在 usertest 中的某个地方。
I think the resulting experience is that somewhere in usertest.
一个特定的 usertest ，执行大量 fork 和执行，
A particular usertest and do a lot of forking and executing,
你会得到一个问题，
you're going to get a problem,
你会得到一个错误，
and you get an error,
在错误中，出错的是，
in the error, the thing that goes wrong is that,
如果从父进程复制，
if you copy from the parent process,
如果父进程在子进程之前退出，
if the parent process exits before the child process does,
那么父进程页表会被彻底清理掉，
then the parent process page table will be completely clean up, right,
正如我们之前看到的，
as we saw before,
然后，子进程仍然具有指向父进程页表的指针，
and then the child still has pointers to the parent process pagetable
所以基本上你会，
and so basically you're gonna,
基本上子进程中的页表已经处理过，
basically pages in this child process pagetable have been [treat]
而且仍在使用，
and they're still used,
其结果就是各种不良行为，
as a result in all kinds of bad behavior,
因为内核释放页面，
because the kernel wanted free the page
实际上在里面写入 1 ，
actually writes ones in it everywhere,
为了调试的原因，
for debugging reasons
所以现在你有，
and so now basically you have
无效的 pte 在你的内核页表中。
invalid you know ptes sitting in your kernel pagetable.
这个能理解吗。
Does that make sense.
好的，下一个。
Okay, one more.
你可以查看 exec.c 。
You can do to look at exec.c.
在我的解决方案中，是很直截的，
In my solutions, are pretty straightforward,
没有修改 exec 。
always made no modifications to exec.
唯一的修改是，
The only modification away,
当然，你知道第一部分的第一个，
of course you know the first thing for, you know, part one,
接下来是第三部分，
and then here for part three,
将新用户页表映射到内核页表。
which is basically mapping the new user pagetable into the kernel pagetable.
exec 基本上是这样做的，
Exec basically does,
我们构建了一个新的用户地址空间，
we built a new user address space
这一行复制新用户地址空间到内核页表。
and you know there's one line copies of new user address space into the kernel pagetable.
就是这样。
And that's it.
有什么问题吗。
Any questions.
所以，希望在此期间，
So, hope in the meantime,
我已经回答了你们提交的很多问题，
I've answered many of the questions that you submitted,
我们可以看看有哪些，
we can look and see which ones,
还有几个问题，
there were a couple more questions
我还没讨论过。
that I haven't talked about yet.
所以也许我们可以看看那些，
So maybe we can look at those
或者你有问题要问。
or unless you have questions right away.
嗯，我们也要修改 growproc 吗？
Um, don't we modify the growproc as well?
是的，还有几处需要修改，
Yes, there are a couple more changes are necessary,
在 sbrk 或 growproc 中。
you know in sbrk or growproc.
有一个，我这里有一行，
There's a, I had a line right here,
类似的方式，也有类似的修改。
similar style and there's presumably a similar change in.
再说一次，[可能在这里]，
Again I might be it actually,
[经常在这里]，
usually in it of course,
它可能不得不改变。
it probably has to change.
因为你必须将初始化代码中的一页映射到，
Because you have to map that one page from the init code into the,
进程中的内核页表。
the kernel pagetable for you in that process.
因为第一个进程很特别。
Because the first process is special.
好的，现在我要浏览一下这里的一些问题，
Okay so I'm gonna walk through some of the questions here
我把它们放到屏幕上，
and I put them on the screen,
所以你们可以看到它们。
so you can helpful see them.
其实我不一定要把它们全部读出来。
Actually I don't have to [] read them out completely.
第一个问题是，
I think the first question is a question
关于 pte_u 标志位的，
that came up quite a bit about the pte_u bit flag,
我想我们已经讨论过了，
I think we've covered this,
我们还讨论了，
we also cover the fact
它不是防止恶意行为的，
that it's not malicious,
而是主要出于调试的原因。
but it's mostly for debugging reasons.
类似的问题，比如，
Similar question about like,
如果你在管理者模式，你能做任何事情吗，
well if you're supervisor mode, can you do anything,
因为你可以切换 satp ，
because you can switch the satp,
你可以，嗯。
you can, um.
答案是肯定的，
And the answer is yes,
也有可能，所以它是，
also possible and so it really
这个 u 标志位不是关于
you know this u bit is not about
保护用户程序不受内核影响，
the user program being protected from the kernel,
实际上是作为标志位帮助内核开发人员，
was really as a flag to help the kernel developer
用于构建内核。
and build the kernel.
另一个特殊的 RISC-V 问题，
One other specific RISC-V question,
为什么在 proc.h 的 trapframe 中，
which is why are they in trapframe proc.h,
寄存器是这种奇怪的顺序。
the register should have been a in the strange order.
原因是，
And the reason that is,
我们之前提到过，
I think we mentioned this a little while ago,
在上一节课中，
in the previous lecture,
有一种叫做 RISC-V 压缩指令集的东西，
basically there's something that's called the RISC-V compressed instruction set,
它使用一组较少的寄存器。
that has a set of fewer registers.
所以你必须对指令进行更紧凑的编码。
And, so you have to have more compact encoding of instructions.
那么这个奇怪的顺序反映了一个事实，
And um, this strange ordering reflects the fact
它们是压缩版本，
that they're basically to there's the compressed version,
是某组寄存器，
which is some set of registers,
是一种压缩版本，
and then sort of a compressed version,
我们正在使用的，
which is what we're using,
它有一套完整的寄存器。
it has a complete set of registers.
而压缩版本，包含 s1 和 s0 ，
And the compression version, for example has s1 and s0,
s0 和 s1 ，
s0 and one,
但没有 s2 到 s11 。
but not s2 to s11.
所以这是主要原因。
So that's the main reason.
我想我已经回答了大部分问题，
I think I went through most of these questions,
但是如果你看到一个问题，
but if you see a question,
我应该讲却没有讲的问题，
that I should have covered and it didn't,
请打断我，
please interrupt me
或者你可以问我还没有讲到的问题，
or if you ask a question I haven't covered yet,
请问我。
please ask me.
这些问题基本上是按照提交的顺序，
These questions are basically in order that submitted them,
所以这些是。
so these were.
好的，这里可能是。
Okay, here maybe.
这有一个问题，
So here's a question,
对于使用分层页表的操作系统来说，
do operating system using hierarchical pagetables
是否设置过页表页面，
ever to set up the pagetable pages,
让层次结构的较低部分是共享的。
so that the lower parts of the hierarchy, are these part shared.
你看到我的解决方案，
And, you clearly saw my solution correct,
我分享条目 1 到 511 ，
I share the entries one to five eleven
这是一个标准的技巧，
and so this is a standard trick,
很多操作系统都是这么做的。
and lots of operating systems do that.
我想我们讨论了一下这个特别的问题，
I think we talked a little bit about this particular issue
切换到主内核页表是很重要的，
that is important that you switch to this main kernel pagetable,
因为调度程序，
because scheduler,
可能根本没有要运行的用户进程，
there might be no user processes to run at all anymore,
在调度器中，当然还需要一个页表，
in the scheduler of course still needs a pagetable,
因此，它与主内核页表一起运行。
so it runs with the main kernel pagetable.
聊天中的问题。
Question in the chat.
好的，继续。
Yeah go ahead.
聊天中的内容是什么。
What is there when you pull up the chat.
我可以读出来。
I can read it.
是的，我看到了。
Yeah I got it.
所以我想问题是，
So I think you know okay so the question is,
注意到 RISC 特权标准说到，
note the RISC privilege specs saying
隔离的那部分是为了防止 bug ，
that part of the separation is to prevent bugs
允许用户程序使内核跳转到用户空间中的任意代码。
that allow user program to make the kernel jump to arbitrary code in user space.
对，一个很好的观点，
Yes, that's a good point,
所以你可以在这里辩论，
yeah, so you know you can debate here,
是隔离属性或内核调试属性。
one of these is an isolation property or kernel debugging property.
显然，内核永远不应该
Clearly, the kernel should never
直接跳入用户地址空间的任何地址，
jump into any part of the address, the user address space directly,
除非我把它视为一种工具，
until you know I view this as a tool
来帮助内核调试或捕获这些类型的 bug 。
to help the kernel debug or catch those kinds of bugs.
以及为什么对于 xv6 我们禁用或设置 u 标志位。
And some reasons why xv6 we also disable or set the u bit.
并且不允许内核引用任何（用户）页面，
And don't allow the kernel to refer to any pages,
这防止我们，引用用户地址，
that protects us, you know you did reference ever user address,
实际上内核会出错。
that the kernel would actually fault.
我想我也讨论了调度器。
I think I've covered the scheduler point, too.
这里有一个问题，
So here's a question,
xv6 中的管道是如何实现的，
how are pipes implemented in
而且在 pgtlb 实验中修改页表，
and choose change to pagetable implemented the pgtlb lab
怎样影响这个实现。
effect this implementation.
嗯，管道基本上是内核中的一个缓冲内存。
Um, so pipes are basically a buffering memory in the kernel.
还有写，当你写管道的时候，
And write, when you write your pipe,
就是调用 copyin ，
basically calls copyin,
copyin 将字节从用户空间复制到管道中，
and copyin copy the bytes from user space into the pipe,
在某些方面，页表实验的全部内容，
and in some ways you know the whole part of the pgtbl lab,
简化了代码。
basically streamline that code.
所以你不用调用很多 walk ，
So you don't have to do many walks,
当你从用户空间写入管道时。
when you actually you're write from user space into the pipe.
这个问题我想很多人都在问，
This is a question I think a lot of people ask,
为什么 uvmfree 和 freewalk ，
you know like, why did uvmfree and freewalk,
会在叶节点引发错误。
originally panic at a leaf.
原因是，
And the reason is that,
我们把它放到那里，
you know we put that in there,
因为它坏了，这是一个迹象，
because it broke, that was an indication
xv6 中的一个区域将被破坏。
that an area in the xv6 would be broken,
这是未修改的 xv6 的不变量，
that's the invariant for unmodified xv6,
在这种情况下，
in this particular case,
这不是真的，
that is not true,
因此，你必须从根本上避免错误。
and so, you have to basically get rid of the panic.
意识到这个错误并不重要，
And realized that it was not important to panic,
你不应该到达那里。
therefore, you should not get it there.
我觉得我们讨论了不少，
I think we talked quite a bit about,
为什么 vm 复制新的，
why vm copy new's,
为什么新的 vm 副本是好的。
why the new vm copy is good one.
好的，还有一个问题，
Okay, here's another question,
我们看一下，可能是一个有趣的，
let's see this may be an interesting,
一个问题问到了更多的设计问题。
one question was asked for more design question.
我需要这张图片。
I need help have that picture.
我们看一下内核地址空间，
We look at the kernel address space where we limited,
{} {}，
,
我们限制，用户地址用户程序可以更大，
we limited user address user programs can be bigger
用户程序最多可以增长到 CLIENT 地址。
user programs can grow through the CLINT address, no further.
假设我们实际上想要一路增长到这里。
Let's say we actually wanted to grow all the way to here.
我们怎么能做到这一点，
How could we do that,
怎么，
what what,
我们应该如何改变设计来允许这个。
how should we change the design that would allow that.
有人知道吗。
Anybody.
我们是否可以重新映射这些东西，
Could we remap the stuff,
比如 CLINT PLIC 和 UART ？
like CLINT PLIC and UART.
是的，你会在哪里映射，
Yeah, where would you map that,
你想在哪里，
so where if you want to do,
来释放地址空间的那部分，
free up basically that part of the address space,
你能在哪里做（映射）。
where what could you do.
映射到一个地方，
Map into like a custom thing,
在 KERNBASE 之前和，
before KERNBASE and after,
在 PHYSTOP 之前和 KERNBASE 之后。
like before PHYSTOP, and after KERNBASE.
是啊，或者更好的是在 PHYSTOP 之后，
Yeah, or maybe it's better to after PHYSTOP,
这里有大量的自由空间。
here's a huge amount of free space.
比如地址空间没有使用，
Like address space isn't used like this,
从这里到那里都是用于物理内存。
from here to there is basically used for physical memory.
我们可以在这里设置映射，
And we basically could setup mappings here,
例如，我们可以把 UART 放在这里，
for example we could put the UART here,
UART0 ，
UART0,
我们放在 PHYSTOP 旁边，
we can put just about PHYSTOP page,
建立一个映射，
and basically set up a mapping
映射到那个特定的物理地址，
that maps in that particular physical address, right,
那么现在将释放这些映射，
then now will free up this mapping
我们可以把它用作用户空间，
and we could use it for user space,
同样，我们也可以对 UART0 执行此操作，
so similarly we could do that for UART0
或 VIRTIO_disk ， PLIC 和 CLINT 。
or VIRTIO_disk, for PLIC and CLINT.
真正的内核是这样做的。
And real kernels do that.
这个能理解吗。
Does that make sense.
这没有问题吗，
Is it isn't that problematic though,
因为我们会想要同样的映射，
cause we would want the same same mapping
像原来的内核页表一样。
as the original kernel pagetable has.
好的，我们需要对每个内核页表做这个，
Well, we have to do it in every every kernel pagetable,
我们要复制，
we have copies,
我们必须把在特定的位置把它映射到任何地方。
we have to map it everywhere at that particular location.
我不确定是不是，
I'm not sure that is,
不确定是否回答了你的问题，
not sure I answered your question,
但是我不认为这是一个问题。
but I don't think that's a problem.
我明白了，所以你也在原来的（页表）中做这个映射。
I see, so you do that mapping also in the original.
是的，我们也得在原来的做这些。
Yeah we have to do those in the original one.
这很简单，让整个内核统一，
It does easier if the whole kernel uniformly
让 UART0 位于顶端。
thinks about UART0 sitting at the top.
很多人问到，
You know, a number of people ask
为什么我们要将内核堆栈映射到高位置。
why do we map the kernel stacks high up.
那是什么原因呢？
What is the reason for that.
在 procinit 中，我们将这些内核堆栈映射到高处，
Like in procinit, we map these kernel stacks high up
如果你采用复制的方法，
and if you did the copy approach,
你实际上需要修改 procinit ，
you actually have to modify procinit,
复制这个映射。
actually copy over that mapping.
为什么要在虚拟地址空间高位置？
And why sitting in up high virtual address space?
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
是不是因为 RISC-V 中的堆栈向下增长，
Is it specifically because the the stacks in RISC-V grow downwards,
所以你把它放在地址空间的高处，
so you place it high in the address space,
让它有向下增长的空间。
that it has space to grow downwards.
是的，这个方向，要向下增长多少页呢？
Yeah, how much this direction how much page does it have to grow downwards?
那应该没关系，因为它只有一页，对吧。
That shouldn't matter, because it's just one page, right.
是的，只有一页，
Yeah it's only one page,
那么如果你增长超过一页会发生什么呢？
so what happens if you grow on one page?
你到了守护页，对吧。
You run into the guard page, correct.
而守护页没有映射，
And the guard page not mapped
因此内核将会错误，
and so the kernel will panic,
这比覆盖数据结构要好。
which is better than actually writing over its data structures.
所以它在高处的原因是，
So the reason it's high up is
因为我们在它下面放了一个守护页。
because we put a guard page below it.
守护页有没有关联的物理内存？
Is there actually any physical memory associated with that guard page.
没有。
No.
是的，没有与守护页关联的物理内存，
No, there's no physical memory associated with the guard page,
所以把它放得很高的一件很酷的事情，
so that's one of the cool things about putting it high
我们可以放一个守护页面在它下面，
is that we can put a guard page below it
实际上不会消耗任何物理内存。
that actually doesn't really consume any physical memory.
好的。
Okay.
能理解吗。
Does that make sense.
堆栈页面在物理内存的某个地方，
Also, basically the stack staff page will be physical somewhere,
但守护页页不是？
but the guard page won't.
没错。
Exactly.
再说一次，这是使用虚拟内存可以做的很酷的事情之一。
Again, one of the cool things you can do with virtual memory.
有没有可能超过守护页。
Is it possible to overshoot the guard page.
这是个很好的问题
That's a great question,
举个例子，
you know one of one for example is
你分配了（守护页），
you know, you allocated the guar-,
一个堆栈上的缓冲区，
a buffer on the stack
它比守护页大，对吧，
that actually is [] bigger than the guard page, correct,
然后进入下一个内核堆栈页面。
and sort of goes into the next kernel stack page.
是的，你会有一个严重的 bug 。
And yeah you would have a serious bug.
你很可能会遇到这样的情况，
Most likely you will run into that anyway,
因为你将使用缓冲的第一个条目，
because you would use the first entries that buffer,
然后就会得到页面错误。
and then you will get the page fault.
当你走运的时候。
When you get lucky.
所以这不是一种绝对有效的内核调试技术，
So this is not a bulletproof kernel debugging technique,
但事实证明它非常有效。
but it has proved to be extremely effective.
好问题。
Great question.
还有什么问题吗。
Any more questions.
我们回到（问题）列表上。
We'll go back to the list.
我们还有几分钟，
See, we have a couple more minutes
实际上还有一分多钟。
and then actually we have one more minute.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
一旦我们有了进程的内核页表，
so once we have our kernel pagetable for the processes,
这是否意味着在 trap 代码中，
does that mean that in the trap code,
我们不需要切换页表。
we don't need to switch pagetables.
我认为是一个好问题，一个好的设计问题，
I think the great question, a good design question,
答案是肯定的，你不需要它，
and the answer is yes, you don't need it right,
因为，主要原因是
because, the main reason that
内核或者 trampoline 代码，
the kernel or in trampoline code,
我们经历这些麻烦，
we go through all this trouble
是因为我们必须复制用户（页表），
is because we have to copy the user,
我们必须从内核页表切换到用户页表，
we have to switch from the kernel pagetable to the user pagetable,
用户页表或没有其他内核映射的页表。
the user pagetable or a pagetable doesn't have the rest of the kernel map.
嗯，所以，缺点是。
Um, and so, downside.
等等，我不确定这是不是正确的，
Wait, I'm not sure that's true,
因为内核需要有，
because the kernel needs to have the user block,
设置用户标志。
user flag on set.
是的，好的，我有几点想说，
Yeah, okay so there's a couple of points I wanted to make,
原则上，你可以简化，
so in principle, you could simplify,
我这么说吧，
let me put it this way,
你可以简化进入退出，
you can simplify entry and exit,
如果你在内核中有一个单独的页表映射到用户，
if you have a single pagetable that maps the user in the kernel
在单独页表中，
in a single pagetable,
那样你就不用切换了，
because then you don't have to switch,
你需要对 xv6 进行更多修改，
you will have to make a couple more modifications to xv6
才能做到这一点。
to make that happen.
但是，原则上是可以的，
But in principle you could
事实上，直到最近 Linux 使用，
and in fact Linux until very recently used,
这种策略，
you know this sort of strategy
内核和用户代码位于单个页表中，
of where the kernel and the user code are sitting in a single pagetable,
依赖 u 标志位，
in relying on basically u bit,
来确保，
you know to make sure that the,
用户程序无法修改任何内核页面。
the user program couldn't actually modify any kernel pages.
在这种情况下，进入退出代码稍微简单一些，
And the entry exit code in that case is slightly simpler,
因为你不必切换页表，
because you don't have to switch pagetables
当你进入或离开内核时。
when you enter or leave the kernel.
可能会发生一件事，
One thing that happened with
比如，熔断攻击，
for example the meltdown attack,
你可能受到侧通道攻击，
if you might have [] side channel attack,
针对侧通道攻击，
in response to the actually side channel attack,
Linux 切换或作为另一种模式运行，
Linux switch or as another mode of running,
有两种运行模式，一种称为 kpti 模式。
there are two modes of running, one's called kpti mode.
在该模式下，反映了 xv6 所做的事情。
And in that mode, basically that reflects basically what xv6 does.
我们有一个单独的内核页表，
We're having a separate pagetable for the kernel
和一个单独的用户空间页表。
and a separate pagetable for user space.
但我还是不明白这为什么管用，
But I still don't understand why that's that works,
因此，假设每个用户进程和内核使用相同的页表，
so let's say the per user process and the kernel use the same pagetable
如果用户内存必须设置用户位，
if the user memory has to have the user bit set,
内核将无法访问该用户内存。
the kernel will not be able to access that user memory right.
好的。
OK, the.
好的，在英特尔处理器上这不是[规则]，
Okay, on Intel processors that is not the rule,
因此，英特尔处理器，如果设置了 u 标志位，
so for example, Intel processors, if u bit set,
内核仍然可以写入和读取那个页。
the kernel could still write and read that page.
哦，那只是一个 RISC-V 的事情。
Oh, that's just a RISC-V thing.
即使在 RISC-V 上，你也可以修改它，
And even on the RISC-V, you can change it,
在 sstatus 寄存器中有一位，
there's a bit in the sstatus register,
你可以将其设置为某个位，
you can set that to some bit
如果你设置了它，
and if you set that
然后处于内核模式，
then basically in kernel mode,
u 标志位会被忽略。
the u bit is ignored.
好的，你是说这个处理器中的一位，
Okay so you're telling me that there's just one bit in this [] processor
让我晚了四个小时才睡。
that made me stay up four hours later.
是的，我对此非常抱歉，
Yes, I'm very sorry about that,
我早该知道的。
I should have known that.
当你报告后，
When you report,
它让我想起了一个 bug ，
it reminded me of a bug,
我在夏天遇到的，
that I actually had during the summer,
就是那个 bug ，
it was exactly that bug,
但是我忘了这件事。
but I forgot about it.
所以，我对此道歉。
So my apology for that.
不，没关系，
No, it's okay,
这是一个很有趣的事情，
it was a, it was fun figuring it out for sure,
但是在某个时候我就像，
but I at some point I was just like
好吧，要么是我疯了，要么是完全错了，
okay like either I'm crazy or something completely wrong,
所以我去睡觉了，
so I'm just gonna go to sleep
然后提交了这个 piazza 问题，
and submit this piazza post
希望当我醒来的时候，有人会回答，
and hopefully when I wake up, someone will answer,
幸运的是，情况就是这样。
fortunately that was the case,
所以我可以继续[]。
so I was able to just continue [write off] when I when I did.
好的，我想我们有点超时了，
Okay so I think we ran overtime a little bit,
希望这些有帮助，
hopefully this was helpful
并回顾了虚拟内存的东西。
and reaffirm things with virtual memory.
我觉得这件事很重要，
I think it's important to do,
因为我们还会有三个涉及虚拟内存的实验。
because we're going to get three more labs involving virtual memory.
我希望是，
And my hope is that,
在这一次之后，会比这次经历更容易。
after this one you know there's going to be easier than this experience.
我能问个小问题吗？
Can I ask something very quick?
是的，我要留下来，
Yeah yeah I'm I'm staying on,
所以如果有人想留下来，问更多问题，
so everybody wants to stay on and ask more questions,
请随意，
please feel free to do,
如果你需要上下一节课，也可以走。
so if you need to go to the next class, please go.
所以基本上，在所有的实验里，
So basically, in all the labs,
有很多提到，
like there's a lot of mention of,
比如，这在未来的实验里可能会有用，
like oh we, this might be useful in future labs,
但是实际上我们从来没有用过我们写的任何代码，
but we never actually use any of the code that we write,
那个计划是什么，
like what's what's the plan on that,
我们是否应该只从之前的实验导入代码，
like should we just import our code from a previous lab
或者我不想那样，因为如果有 bug ，
or like I don't want to because what if it's bug,
我不想影响下一个实验。
I don't wanna you know impact the next lab.
是的，所以，我们不这么做的一个原因是，
Yeah, so, one reason we don't do it,
为什么实验不是建立在彼此之上，
you know why, why the build labs don't build on each other,
即使它们可以，
even though they could,
就是为了避免基本依赖关系，
is to avoid basic dependencies,
比如，如果你在前面的实验中有个 bug ，
like if you had a bug in earlier lab,
没有被 usertests 检查出，
that was not exposed by usertests
或任何其他测试，
or any of other tests,
但是会暴露在那个新的实验里，
but will be exposed to that new lab,
那你会很痛苦。
then you know be painful.
我提到的原因是，
The reason I'm mentioning that is
这是真实的事情如何发生，
that basically the real thing what's going on,
我们要用页表做更多的事情。
is we're going to do more stuff with pagetables.
例如，这个实验考虑简化 copyin ，
For example, this lab looks at simplifying copyin,
在后面的实验中，我们考虑对 sbrk 的修改，
later labs, we look at change to sbrk,
基本上，我们离你在这个实验中对内核的修改很远。
basically we're far gonna to the changes you made to the kernel for his lab.
但是你知道，你一直考虑，
But you know the fact that you've been thinking about
内核页表，用户页表，会对你有帮助。
kernel pagetable user page tables so much, will help you.
另外，它真的可以帮助你经历调试这类问题，
Plus, it really helps you experience debugging these kinds of problems,
由于页表不正确（的问题）。
due to incorrect pagetables.
好的，我只是想确认一下，
Okay I just want to make sure
我没有错过，
that it's not like I'm missing out,
因为我没有从实验一复制我的 xargs 代码或别的东西。
because I didn't copy over my xargs code from lab one or something.
实验目标不同，它们互不依赖。
Decided to purpose that the labs were not dependent on each other.
好的，谢谢，星期三见。
Okay, thanks, see you on wednesday.
星期三见。
Wednesday.
我有一个关于映射更进一步的问题，
I had a follow up on my question about mapping,
映射使用页表实验中的修改，
mapping using the modification from the pagetable lab,
那么是否需要
would it be then needed to
trampoline 映射到用户页表。
have the trampoline maps in the user pagetables.
好的，我没有想过这个。
Okay so I haven't really thought this through.
所以如果你，假设内核存在，
So if you've kernels, let's say the kernel exits,
因此，假设我们已经关联了一个页表，
so let's say we have join one single pagetable
就像这里显示的一样。
as one here shown, correct.
并且，我们通过 userret 跳出内核。
And, we're jumping out of the kernel through userret.
我们的目标是，我们还在内核模式下运行，
In our goal is to we're still running in kernel mode,
所以内核当然可以访问这个页面。
so this page certainly accessible, correct, in by the kernel.
守护页，
The guard page,
我展示的，
I'll show you,
不是守护页，
do not the guard page, when I'm saying
是 trampoline 页面，
the trampoline pages there,
很可能在某个地方，
and presumably somewhere,
我们需要映射，或许。
we need to map maybe the.
好的，用户 trapframe ，
Well, the user trapframe,
我们并不能访问，
we don't really have access to anyway,
因为我们运行的是内核模式，
because we're running kernel mode,
我们知道它在 proc 结构中，
we know where it sits in the proc structure,
或者我们可以得到它。
or we can get it.
所以我想我们可以退出。
So I think we can just exit.
当你回来的时候，
And when you return,
用户代码可以直接运行，
the user code can just run,
当然 u 标志位是。
you know we of course the u bit is.
但是 u 标志位总是设置页面，
But u bit is always set pages
位于用户空间中，
that actually sit in the user space,
所以这也是好的，
so that's fine too,
因此，当我们重新进入内核时，
so when we enter the kernel back in,
我们仍然使用这个页表，
we're still with this pagetable,
这个页表现在已经映射了所有内核。
that pagetable already has all the kernel that mapped.
我们可以直接复制寄存器，
And we can just you know copy, you know the registers
我们需要保存到 proc 结构中的（寄存器）。
that we need to save into the proc structure directly.
而不必查找单独的页面，
Instead of having to go through separate page
里面有 proc 结构。
with the proc structure in it.
所以我相信修改会相当直接。
So I believe the change will be pretty straightforward.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Okay I see, thank you.
当然，我可能是错的。
Of course, I could be wrong.
好的，我现在去试一下。
Yeah I'm now gonna try it now.